# Martin Skarzynski Laptev

#### Mission

My goal is to lead the next generation of scientists and engineers in building solutions that integrate substantive expertise from diverse fields with machine intelligence. Through my work, I strive to promote open source software, such as the Quarto publishing system, which I use to build dashboards, presentations, reports, websites, and other digital deliverables. Overall, I aim to leverage my broad scientific background and technical expertise to help transform the promises of science and technology into a better future for all of humanity.

# **Recent Experience**

# **Lead Instructor**, General Assembly

July 2019 - Present

- Teaches open-enrollment and enterprise courses such as:
  - React Development
- Data Analytics

Tech Excellence Data Science

- Python Programming
- Front-End Web Development

### **Lead Instructor**, Data Society

October 2019 - Present

- Provides enterprise clients with training in:
  - Machine Learning
- DevOps

Python Programming

- R Programming
- Graph Analytics
- Natural Language Processing

# Vice President, Data Community DC

April 2022 - Present

Leads a non-profit organization that supports <u>eleven Meetup groups</u>

#### **Adjunct Professor**, Virginia Tech

September 2021 - December 2023

- Taught two graduate courses for the Computer Science and Statistics Departments:
  - Machine Learning
- Data Analytics

#### Senior Domain Lead, Amazon Web Services &

April 2022 - February 2023

- Provided customers with scientific and technical expertise in:
  - Computer Vision
- Data Architecture
- Data Visualization

Genomics

- Machine Learning
- Real World Evidence
- Built Artificial Intelligence (AI) solutions and Machine Learning Operations (MLOps) systems using:
  - Amazon SageMaker
- AWS Developer Tools
- AWS Lambda

- Amazon EventBridge
- AWS CloudFormation
- AWS IAM

Amazon EMR

- AWS Databases
- AWS Service Catalog

- Obtained 3 AWS certification
  - Solutions Architect Associate
- Cloud Practitioner
- Practical Data Science

#### **AI Engineering Manager**, Booz Allen Hamilton

October 2019 - March 2022

- Led a team of data scientists and software developers working on a cyber intelligence application
- Spearheaded interdisciplinary COVID-19 visualization, genomics, and statistical modeling efforts
- Obtained the Microsoft Azure Data Scientist Associate certification

### **Biomedical Scientist**, National Institutes of Health

June 2009 - April 2021

- · Integrated clinical, laboratory, epidemiologic, genomic, and medical imaging data
- Combined deep learning and statistical inference using stacked ensembles
- Conducted genomic analysis of immune and cancer cells
- Developed and tested pharmaceutical and immunotherapeutic agents
- · Quantified cancer cell signaling pathways
- Mentored trainees from various NIH training programs including:

• SIP • MRSP • HISTEP

# **Bioinformatics and Data Science Co-Chair, FAES**

January 2014 - May 2020

- Co-administered an academic program with over twenty faculty members
- Taught three graduate data science courses:
  - Introduction to Python
     In
    - Introduction to Text Mining
- Applied Machine Learning
- Taught graduate biotechnology workshops on various topics including:
  - Pharmacometrics
- Cellular Immunology
- Flow Cytometry

# Adjunct Professor, George Washington University

January 2015 - May 2015

- Taught two undergraduate courses for the Women's Leadership Program:
  - Biology of Organisms
- Women and Leadership

#### Education

<ul> <li>MPH, Epidemiology and Biostatistics, <u>Johns Hopkins University</u></li> </ul>	May 2018
PhD, Tumor Biology, Georgetown University	May 2015
MS, Biotechnology, <u>Jagiellonian University</u>	June 2009
BA, Biology, St. Mary's College of Maryland	May 2007

#### **Select Publications**

March 2023	<ul> <li>Recalibration of a deep learning model [] to inform lung cancer screening intervals</li> </ul>
May 2022	SARS-CoV-2 genome-based severity predictions correspond to [] higher viral load
April 2022	• Linking genotype to phenotype [] in SARS-CoV-2 []
June 2021	Variants in SARS-CoV-2 associated with mild or severe outcome
January 2021	Using prediction models to reduce [] disparities in [] lung cancer screening []
July 2016	• Pathogenic role of [BCR] signaling and canonical NF-κB activation in [MCL]
January 2016	• Interactions between ibrutinib and anti-CD20 antibodies []
December 2015	Health disparities in the immunoprevention of [HPV] [] associated malignancies
May 2015	Designing the furin-cleavable linker in recombinant immunotoxins []
October 2014	• Harnessing the Fcμ receptor for [] therapy of [CLL]

# **Select Awards**

•	Community Contribution of the Year Category Finalist, AWS Builder Awards	February 2023
•	Artificial Intelligence Solutions Architect Award, BAH Emergent Skills Program	January 2022
•	Trans-Fellowship Research Award. Cancer Prevention Fellowship Program	June 2019

# **Natural Languages**

Native: English, Polish
 Professional: Spanish, Russian
 Working: French, Portuguese